George Gamow and Barbara Gamow Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Speeches and Writings File, 1926-1970 (Box 15-27)
  - Books
    - Mr. Tompkins in Paperback (1965) (Box 24)
      - Typescript, (5 folders)
      - Manuscript fragment
      - Miscellany
    - Mr. Tompkins Inside Himself (1967)
      - Preface
      - Corrections and correspondence
      - Illustrations, (2 folders)
    - Mr. Tompkins Learns the Facts of Life (1953), preface not used, 1964
    - My World Line (1970)
      - Manuscripts, circa 1968
        - Chapters 1-3
        - Chapters 4-7
      - Final typescripts (Box 25)
      - Illustrations, notes, index
      - Galleys
      - Draft, conclusions, miscellany
      - Miscellaneous notes, articles, sources
      - Reviews, miscellany
      - Uncorrected proof
    - "Relativity, Gravity, and Cosmology," preface, 1964 (not published)
    - "The Sacred Grove," George Gamow's translation of a poem by Edmond Rostand
    - A Star Called the Sun (1964), typescript carbon, (2 folders)
    - Thirty Years That Shook Physics (1966) (Box 26)
      - Manuscript, (5 folders)
      - Typescript, (3 folders)
    - "The Universe in the Making," manuscript, (2 folders)
    - Printed versions (Box 27)
      - Biography of Physics (1961), annotated
      - The Creation of the Universe (1952), with reviews and correspondence laid in
    - One, Two, Three... Infinity (1947), annotated with correspondence from Albert Einstein laid in
    - Thirty Years That Shook Physics (1966), annotated with reviews laid in (2 copies)
- Miscellany, 1931-1974 (Box 28-30)
  Newspaper clippings, printed matter, scrapbooks, correspondence, miscellaneous personal records, notes, drawings, greeting cards, book reviews, and other material.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material. Final box contains oversize awards, certificates, a drawing, and illustrations, arranged alphabetically by type of material, title, or subject.
  - Bibliographical and biographical material regarding George Gamow, circa 1940-1973, undated, (7 folders) (Box 28)
  - Calendar and address book, 1968
  - Consulting agreements, 1956-1958
  - Cosmology research notes
  - Drawings by George Gamow (Box 29)
  - Faust; Eine Historie
  - Lecture invitations, 1956-1957
  - Medical charts and related matter., 1947-1968
  - Memorial building lectures, 1969-1974
  - Notes, cards, and travel itineraries
  - Obituaries and lists, 1968
  - Printed matter, (2 folders)
  - Reviews and comments on George Gamow's books, 1959-1966
  - "RNATIE Club," 1954-1955, 1966 (Box 30)
  - Russian poems from memory, undated
  - Scrapbooks, "A Gamovian Miscellany," 1931-1968, (3 vols.)
- Addition, 1950-1967 (Box 31)
  Letters received and mostly copies of letters sent by George Gamow.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or topic.
  - Brosche, Peter, 1967 (Box 31)
  - Herman, Robert, 1965-1967
  - Letters related to Immanuel Velikovsky, 1950
  - Yčas, Martynas, 1967
- Oversize, 1951-1970 (Box OV 1)
  Awards and certificates, illustrations, miscellaneous drawings, photography album, and other oversize items.
  Arranged alphabetically according to subject of type of material.
  - Awards and certificates, 1951-1965 (Box OV 1)
  - Book illustrations
    - Matter, Earth, and Sky (1958)
    - Thirty Years That Shook Physics (1966), (7 folders)
  - Garage window decorations, undated
  - Miscellaneous drawings, 1961, undated
  - Lukas, Jerry, photograph album drawing, 1970
  - Manuscripts and illustrations, (19 folders)